Welcome to The Lighter Side of the Spectrum, the podcast
that celebrates the multiple hats we wear and the juggling
acts we perform in life. Whether you're parenting kids and
teens on the autism spectrum, navigating the ever-evolving healthcare industry,
or building a more inclusive and impactful world, this is
your space to find connection, inspiration, and growth. Together, we'll
share stories, tackle challenges, and explore how innovation and inclusion
create better outcomes for everyone. Because no matter the spectrum,
there's always a lighter side. Now here's your host, David
Kaufer.
Hello again, everybody, and welcome back to The Lighter Side
of the Spectrum.
What if a person understands exactly what you are asking,
but their body cannot reliably carry out the response?
And what if it looks like refusal is actually a
motor planning problem?
And what if that gets labeled as lack of comprehension?
You know, it's really a disconnect between intention and action.
For many nonspeaking and unreliably speaking autistic people, communication
cannot be understood separately from movement.
The body is part of the conversation.
So welcome back to The Lighter Side of the Spectrum,
where we talk honestly about autism, communication, parenting, and what
becomes possible when we presume competence.
My guest today, and I'm super excited about this, is
Dr.
Antigone
Oriopoulos,
a
physiotherapist, researcher, disability advocate, inclusion specialist,
consultant, and coach based in Edmonton, Alberta. Antigone has dedicated
much of her work to increasing awareness of the sensory
motor challenges
experienced by people without reliable speech. She advocates for earlier
and ongoing physiotherapy,
greater recognition of motor planning differences, and access to motor-based
communication for people
with neurodevelopmental disabilities.
She also brings a very unique combination of clinical knowledge
research expertise and practical experience supporting movement through
activities including gymnastics and swimming.
And she's also a mom. Antigone, welcome to The Lighter
Side of the Spectrum.
Thank you so much. I'm very excited to be here
and have a conversation with you. Yeah, yeah, we actually
get to have a conversation, um, as is often the
case here with The Lighter Side of the Spectrum and
some of these great guests that I'm able To connect
with, you know, we've been able to connect, share information,
share a passion, right, for
this community and our work to support
motor-based communication. But why don't you start giving us a
little bit more of your background,
maybe even more as a mom, and kind of what
brought you into this field and kind of your lived
experience?
Sure.
So my first degree was in physiotherapy. I have a
BSc PT.
And
then I,
I practiced 1 year on cardiovascular surgery and cardiology, and
I wanted to try my hands at research. So I
did my master's.
And then at that point, I realized I enjoyed doing
research more than I missed being a clinician. So I
went to do my PhD in public health. And at
that point, I
made the decision actually to let my license go.
I thought that I would never need it or want
it again. And it was— Hmm. Not an easy decision
because I knew there was no coming back to it.
Mm-hmm.
And then I had a child with nonspeaking autism.
And,
and then when I
became more educated on his
condition and realized that his
primary challenge was his sensory motor impairment, it occurred to
me that there's, there's this whole population that really
needs and could benefit from the scope of physiotherapy. So
Lucky for me, one of my very young classmates had
developed a bridging program for
Canadian grads who had moved in out of practice or
international grads preparing for their national exam. There's this program
that I could take for 6 months to get my
license back, and I— Oh, okay. Yeah. So I, I
had no idea what I was gonna do with my
license, 'cause at that point I,
um,
I, I gave up my career in public health.
I, I thought, I thought that that was,
that was it. I'm going to just, I'm going to
be a good caregiver and a good homeschool teacher for
my son. And,
and, but I got my license back and
then just slowly I found and I made opportunities to,
to
get back into practice. And I'm, I'm so thankful I
get to do that. I feel very lucky that I
get to. Yeah.
Okay. I was gonna ask about that. Okay. Yeah. And
he uses a letterboard to communicate and we found
the letterboard for him. I stumbled upon it like most
of us do by accident when he was 4 and
3/4.
Okay, so pretty, pretty young at least. I mean, that's
pretty young. That's cool. Yeah. Yeah. And,
you know, of course, I had to unlearn everything I
thought about, about what I knew about him, including what
they told me, which was
that he had
little to no receptive language and was severely cognitively delayed.
And, um,
and then
Um,
yeah, I had to unlearn all that. And yeah, you
do, you deprogram and kind of reprogram. So how old
was he? Better. Yeah, right. How old was he when
he got diagnosed?
3.
Okay. 3 years old. Yeah.
So then, you know, a little bit of a gap.
Let's— I want to jump into kind of like when
the body doesn't cooperate in that world, because again, I
think, you know, to your credit, you recognized that early
on with your son, um, earlier than a lot of
us did, right? And again, like you said, know better,
do better.
How do you explain the disconnect between intention and movement?
You know, for people who may not understand, you know,
again, for a neurotypical person, it seems totally natural, right?
Right. I think that it really doesn't help that the
DSM, which is what North America uses for the definition
of autism and diagnostic criteria, It's really not helping us
that, that, um,
yeah, the, the language they use is, is really
based on subjective observation, and they focus on
deficits in social communication and social interaction. And they use
language that really implies deliberate intent behind these
behaviors.
And it's really shaped how society has—
viewed autism. And so we're faced with this
just pervasive perspective that is so widespread, it's very difficult
to change. And
it's frustrating and sad because when we compare it to
other
neurological conditions like Parkinson's, Tourette's, catatonia, right? Like,
when we see someone with Parkinson's struggling, they're struggling to
move their body, we don't say, oh, we need to
reduce their behaviors.
Right. We cut them slack and we understand that they're
trying to organize their body. And we look at it
through a motor
challenge lens, not a social lens, which most of the
world looks through autism.
That's a really interesting point. Sorry, I just want to
jump in because you're right. I think
that so dominates the
conversations so often, right?
Behavior, right? And we'll get into this some more. It's
such a negative word. It's only a negative word in
autism.
Right. And outside of that, that sphere, it's, it's sort
of a— Kind of neutral, right? Just kind of like—
It's neutral. Yeah. But with autism, it's, it carries a
lot of negative connotation.
And, uh, there is,
so the latest evidence shows that the sensory motor impairment
causally explains the differences that we see in social communication
and, and social interaction.
And there's,
there's a number of us researchers who are advocating for
motor impairment to be added to the DSM as a
core descriptor, but it's not yet. And so when,
when I— I mean, that's great. It should be.
Yeah, that's a really great point. That absolutely should be
because that's— and I'm sorry to cut you off there.
But again, I just, I go back to this.
It's such a core area when you're talking about this,
particularly again, the nonspeaking autistic population. But it's not even—
it's not even on most people's radar. Exactly,
exactly. It's not even on the radar. Like, we are
so in the dark, and, you know, until you stumble
upon it. But the research is not that new. Like,
the research that's showing
the
motor impairment is
I don't know. Not— it's not—
goes back, well, probably earlier, but like the bulk of
it, 10 or 15 years. So we're not— So it's
there.
It's there. It's this, this— the knowledge translation gap or
the knowledge to action gap is
very wide and very pervasive.
When I, when I do explain to parents, um, client
parents and colleagues
that disconnect, um, because that's one of the first things
I try to tell them, I don't use my own
words because I know what that feels like. But I
do have this, a, a video and a transcript of
2 of our local spellers here. They're, they're young adults,
Peyton Thorpe and Marcus Hulette.
And, and they, um,
I share their words because no matter how well I
explain it, I, my words will never land as well
as theirs. So I can read you these 2 paragraphs.
I would love it. Yeah, I was gonna say, yeah,
let's, let's hear their words. They're both about, uh, they
were, uh, Book 21 when they wrote this. This is
about a year ago.
So Peyton says, my body often feels like it has
a mind of its own. It's a constant battle to
get my limbs to cooperate. I have to find where
I am in space, fight motor loops and repetitive stims,
and try to make my motions smooth. It's like I'm
running a race, but my brain is watching from the
stands and my body is spinning in circles and running
backwards. My brain understands, but it's like my body is
daydreaming. And Marcus responds with, my daydreaming body is the
perfect analogy. My body is like a puppy that just
watched a rabbit run by. It knows what it should
do, but the pull of other things makes it almost
impossible.
Imagine wanting to pick up a glass of water, but
when you go to reach for it, your hand isn't
there. So you find your hand flapping by your head
and you can't get it to move. And just as
your frustration kicks in, your hand starts to move and
you knock the cup over. Mm-hmm.
And then Peyton adds, struggle, frustration, jerky movements repeated. The
despised mantra of my existence.
Wow. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, that's just so—
wow, that's really powerful and just so descriptive. And
yeah, I mean, I'm kind of speechless because, you know,
you hear different variations of that. Stone, you know, my
son Stone has shared, you know,
His, his variations. And the one consistent part is that
talking about the disconnect between the brain and the body—
my body's doing things my brain doesn't want it to
do, or, you know, my body won't do what my
brain wants it to do. And I just can't imagine
the frustration. No.
I just can't. Like, again, I know, like, in a
limited way—
I mean, very limited, not even comparable— but like You
know, when I, I suck at golf, okay? Like, I
try to play golf
and I know how frustrated I get just when I
can't hit the golf ball, right? You feel like you
should. Here's the, the ball sitting there, you swing, it
should be really simple. You don't. You get mad at
that. And that's just a stupid game. Now imagine just
trying to function, like, function every day. This is what
they are,
are fighting with every, every day. And one thing I
learned in a
parent course, um, a few years back in
Of course, from Philadelphia.
I love that they, they said,
um, so if we're talking about brain function, so that
being auditory processing, visual processing, gross motor function, fine motor,
our, our ability to talk,
um, if we call, call that brain function,
there is no correlation between brain function and intelligence. People
confuse the two all the time, but there is high
correlation between
problems in brain function or brain injury, you could say,
and the ability to express that intelligence.
Absolutely.
And again, that's something that you see consistently across the
population.
Now, you know, with behavior, and again, kind of talking
about intent, one of the things you— when you mentioned
that, it just brought back memories of something else that
Stone had talked about, which is
When we had our foray into ABA.
So, um, as many parents did, right? Uh, and I
don't know if, if
you probably were able to avoid it given— Yeah, almost.
We had like 6 months. You're right, I, I did
for the most part avoid it. Just about 6 months
I had it.
Oh, okay. So you, so you were at— you at
least had some experience with it, and, and it's just—
yeah. And because I'm just curious, so, so why did
you do it? Because the social worker told me to.
Right. Okay. That's, yeah, that, I was gonna say, that's
the answer, right? The gatekeepers of this, of the funds
and the services,
they're, they come at, they, for level 3 autism, it's
the triad of oral speech therapy, behavioral therapy, and occupational
therapy. And what are you supposed to do when you
don't know any better?
You do it. And all this. And, and the thing
is, the research does not support Good quality functional outcomes
with that for, for nonspeaking autism, especially for communication. It's
not supported yet. They keep like a lot of money.
I'm a provider. I'm not just a mom, but like
I, I, I get government contracts and there's a lot
of money being thrown at ineffective services and it's
tragic. That's time taken away from a, like a,
um, a child's childhood. Yeah. And, and of course, could
be directed,
um, for more
effective therapy.
Yeah, no, you're absolutely right. And like I said, so
I think about that, and I remember, like I said,
we didn't do it for a super long period. It
was a couple years maybe. I mean, you know, too
long for our purposes because again, it really didn't address
anything
for us. I mean, our goal, like so many other
parents for so long, was just, we just, you know,
we want help our child communicate. I mean, that's what
the goal was, and did nothing for that. But Stone
has since been able to tell me about how
he would dread these appointments because he knew that he,
you know, because they, they do these little
score sheets, right? And, you know, the compliance. And he,
and he talks about how, you know, he hated how
it'd be called non-compliant when he couldn't do— physically couldn't
do something, right, that they were trying to get him
to do. Yeah.
And there was this whole, um, you know, reward and
punishment structure. And, you know, kind of like, oh, well,
if he doesn't score in this percentile, then
you need to take away something. In his case, it
was, um, a cartoon that he loved to watch called
the Little Einsteins. I don't know if it's
still, still a favorite, but anyway, he, he said he,
he knew that whenever he had ABA, it means that
he wouldn't be able to watch Little Einsteins.
Oh, that's so sad. Isn't it? Like, like, that's how,
you know, that was the association he had with it.
So anyway, I mean, that's just It just shows how
backwards it is in terms of, of,
you know, the approach. And the approach is backwards because
they were the— especially the ABA, they're trying to
control and change behavior, but that— it requires
volitional control over your motor system. That's like a top-down
approach. But if you don't have the foundation,
of autonomous motor control, you're going to go— it's going
to do nothing, do nothing except cause trauma.
And there's no behavior really, when you think about it,
that needs to be changed. I mean, at least in
our case. And I know there are some cases of
people who have some pretty severe
challenges. And again, not to say it was 100% worthless,
and I don't mean to spend our time bashing on
ABA, but just think about the different approaches between, like
I said, just thinking about behavior versus just understanding that
brain-body disconnect. So we'll kind of use that as a
bridge, right? Like, we'll talk about,
you know, physiotherapy. Okay. Why don't you introduce us to
that and how that helps and what the difference is
there?
Sure. So,
so right now, the motor impairment in autism is
considered a dual diagnosis of
autism plus developmental coordination disorder.
The
largest study from the SPARK study shows that— I think
the statistic is
at least 90%
of people with autism, and that includes the
more
severe autism or level 3 autism— 90% have motor impairment.
That's huge. And I just want to interject real quick.
Can you just let our listeners know what the SPARK
study was?
provide some context there. Yeah, so Anandja Bhat, B-H-A-T, she
was the
researcher in,
um, in the study. And they,
they met— they measured—
well, it was about 14,000
participants filled out the survey for a DCD screening questionnaire.
So that's— you do what— sorry, so any parent, teacher,
provider can fill out the DCD questionnaire and it, and
it gives you a measure of sort of risk of
motor impairment. But it's, it's pretty,
uh, the psychometric properties are pretty good. So if, if
they're, if, if you're flagged, there's a good chance you
have motor impairment. And it also, that study also showed
the more severe
symptoms of autism, like without being, without functional speech, call
that more severe symptom, the worse your motor impairment Okay.
So,
um, the— and DCD in autism was
added to the DSM, I think it was in 2015,
so a while ago.
The process to assess DCD was developed before they knew
that the prevalence of motor impairment and DCD in autism
was so high.
But I have, um,
I've administered the motor— the standardized test to people like
our children. And
it's really problematic because they,
you find that they all fall under basically below the
first percentile. So that means that these tests, yeah, are
not sensitive enough to get a good baseline. The floor
of the scoring system is way too high. So it's
basically impossible, almost impossible to get a DCD diagnosis in
nonspeaking autism.
Um, but I do think it's— you don't necessarily
need the diagnosis, but I do believe it's important to
have the motor impairment documented so that
the team knows.
Um, that's what I was going to ask then. What
are your options to do that? I mean, for parents,
what are your options to try to screen for motor
impairment or motor differences? What, you know, if they're noticing
things
What can they do?
So
this is something I'm, I'm
starting to teach other physiotherapists and occupational therapists, is that,
um, is that you can pull,
you can pull tasks and, and tests from other standardized,
um, other, other more tests of motor function. So
I kind of do a, a combination myself. So right
now there's no consensus. This is part of the problem
is that there's no consensus on how to measure motor
impairment, especially in
level 3 autism. Nonspeak, like particularly nonspeaking? No, but in
general what I do is I'll take the motor milestones
because those are, those, um, like anyone can Google those
and those would basically be
the rolling,
army crawling, um, Yeah, like 4-point crawling. Okay, jumping, ball
handling skills,
balancing on on one foot, and
you know a squat sits to stand. So there's yeah
there's those kind of motor milestones.
I would assess those. And by the way, when you
the the
the funny thing is is that
the this the majority of thought is. These guys don't
need physical intervention or physiotherapy because we see them walking,
we see them climbing stairs. Right. So there's no problem,
right?
Right. But when you actually go in and, and look
at their
motor function and go back to those motor milestones, there
are so many gaps.
There are like these, these skills that are foundational for
brain development, um, including the higher order ones like,
like speech. They're, they're missing.
They're missing. And,
um, so I'll find out where the gaps in their,
in their motor function are. And Elizabeth Torres developed 3
really simple, really great validated,
uh, functional measures.
2 minutes of sitting still, can they do that? 2
minutes of pointing to a target, and 2 minutes of
walking. So I use— I've just begun to incorporate those
ones as well.
That's great. I have to say though, there's
Sure. It's difficult to find
PTs and OTs who have experience working with
nonspeaking autism to do
an adequate motor function assessment. Like,
it's a problem right now, even though I can't speak
for the US curriculum, but the CDD in autism was
introduced in the OT and PT curriculums about 8 or
9 years ago in Canada.
But it's only taught at a superficial level, like most
specializations. But this is where we're at. There's,
there's, um,
there's this knowledge gap that we're trying to correct, but
parents will find that it is, that it is going
to be a challenge to find a practitioner who has
that experience to administer the test. And not impossible, but—
So in some ways it Feels a little bit like,
kind of like where even autism diagnosis was 20 years
ago, like how difficult it was for parents back then.
I mean, I know it's still not like super easy,
but it's at least easier. I mean, it's more obviously
more pervasive and
yeah, a little more accessible. But that was like, you
know, kind of winning a lottery ticket is if you
were able to get, you know, get in and be
assessed within 12 months or the waiting periods are just
insane.
In Canada, it's, it's, it's laughable now. It's something in
Ontario, it's something like,
I've heard even 6, 7 years and it's 4 to
5 years here in my province. Like— For a diagnosis?
For the assessment. If you want it publicly funded. Oh,
for the assessment. Oh, for, okay. So for the autism
assessment or for— Yes.
Wow.
And to get start earlier intervention. Yes. Early
start, early intervention. You have to wait 5 years.
I know, it's laughable. I like— yeah, I know, it's
awful. Wow. Yeah, that's a, that's a real, that's a
real problem. You touched on this a little bit, but,
um, can you talk a little bit more about what
can happen over time when some of these physical needs
are ignored, or some of these, you know, milestones that
you had talked about?
Yeah, I've, I've worked with enough
enough clients now, um, at different ages that I can
see that I've seen changes
happen that,
that make me, um, that have really made me think
about what these—
this population is going to be like in their 60s
and 70s. And I
truthfully, I lose sleep over this because,
um, because
the way we are, the way it is now, there's
a lot of them that are not going to receive
physical intervention and they're going to age this way. And
of course, we know that they're at higher risk for
comorbidities. They have an accelerated rate of aging because of
inflammation, and they're at higher risk of Parkinson's symptoms and
other comorbidities down the line.
And of course, at this point, still the majority
who don't have communication will not be able to tell
someone when they're in pain. So I, I think about
this all the time.
And,
and I have seen even some individuals in their 20s
who have some postural changes already. Often from— oh yeah,
you had mentioned that. I remember you talking about that.
Often from stimming and sitting in a poor position. But
I've even seen, um, children who are just— who
can't sit to stand without using their hands, which is
kind of like what, what elderly people do.
And I see a lot who have core weakness and
especially upper body weakness just from lack of activity overhead.
And
what I know is that So I don't know if
you've ever had a sort of an overuse injury or
an imbalance that you've had to correct. It's not easy.
It takes like kind of dedicated—
You're right.
It takes time and attention. You have to sort of
like put in the work to correct something.
And often that takes the skill of isolating a muscle
and, or maybe relaxing into a stretch. 2 things that
are very, very difficult for
People with significant motor impairment and autism. So
once you have one of those problems begin, now you're
really facing a mountain now to try and correct. And
that's not impossible,
but prevention of these, of loss of range of motion,
of weakness,
of pain, it's really crucial to have. And we know
that, we know that movement and exercise, that's one of
the One of the things we can hopefully control in
our lives and, and, and do for ourselves to help,
um, age healthy.
So these— But also, does it— does also that they're
also the argument, or just, you know, that's sort of
the argument, but just the point that it can help
with regulation. It could help in other areas too.
That's excellent point. It can also help with regulation,
um,
which
just
Helps with being able to participate in life more.
And, and for if they have access to communication.
Yeah. And self-esteem, of course, when you feel more competent
in your
motor control, you have more confidence. And it's,
it's just beneficial for in so many areas.
And also, there's probably
some benefit Circling back to, we talked about, you know,
communicating with a letterboard, whether it's pointing or typing,
doing a type, a lot of physical activity to help
with that. I mean, that, that's got to be connected
too, right? Speech is just one
pathway in the brain to get out our language, but
there's others. So like our kids,
they can't, they, or can't easily access the speech pathway
because of their different Trajectory in development, but they can
access it through gross motor movement with pointing
because that's sort of that, like if there's a hierarchy
of development, that one came first. So that's,
um,
with practice, that, that one is more accessible.
But it's, but it all, but it's still, it's still
a movement that takes
postural control, motor planning, coordination, visual attention. The ability to
initiate. So
there's this misconception that pointing
is really simple, but it's not.
Oh, yeah.
They're coordinating an incredibly complex sequence of motor tasks when
they do that because you need—
a lot of them
can't feel their pelvis very well. And typically
almost all of our movement is initiated from the trunk
and pelvis. So you need that postural control and stability.
Otherwise, it's much harder to make precise movements. You need
head control to orient yourselves to the, to the board
or the, the, the screen or into your communication partner.
And the eyepiece, there are almost all neurodevelopmental disorders have
a component where
there's visual,
visual motor and ocular motor challenges. We have 12 cranial
nerves. 4 of them alone are dedicated to the eyes.
Wow. That's how important the eyes are. Oh,
Ability to, to generate smooth, controlled movement.
And it's interesting, just on that point with eye control,
I know
when you're talking about, again, nonspeakers and the inability to
communicate, the frustration is they can't tell you if, you
know, if their, if their vision's messed up. And I
know, how many times have we seen within the community
examples
Of, you know, younger— we're not even younger spellers, but
new spellers who, you know, gain communication.
And then like, we, you know, they got glasses, or—
Yeah, they see all— Everything was like they were seeing
double. Everything was double vision. Yeah. And they were trying
to like—
my, again, my gosh, trying to, trying to function in
life, let alone then trying to spell. Like you're trying
to pick which letter to point to and
I mean, such a huge challenge.
Yeah, to be able to have that,
that vision assessment by an optometrist and for my son
to be able to answer questions, that was just,
um,
yeah, like
incredibly helpful because, yeah, my son wears glasses when he
uses a letterboard. His glasses actually have a, um, a
tint to them. He's a bit light sensitive, so, and
he wears prism glasses to help In theory, correct his
center of gravity, his visual processing for when we're doing
gross motor skills. So
yeah, the eyes are like— people forget about how, um,
how important they are. And
to— And then again, if you can't communicate, like my,
my, my eyes/glasses story with Stone was, you know, from
a few, a few years ago,
not long after he was able to communicate. We were
able to figure out somehow— I was able to figure
out he needed glasses, but even getting the right prescription,
then we finally got it and we went down, you
know, we live in
Yeah, Edmonds, Washington, which is right on the Puget Sound.
We have a beautiful— we have a nice beach that
we've spent a lot of time at. And on a
clear day, you can actually look out to the west
and see the Olympic Mountain Range. It's
beautiful, you know, the snow-capped mountains, especially in the winter.
But Stone told me, uh, again, this was like so
powerful a couple years ago. He said, you know, this
is the first time I've been able to see the
Olympic Range.
Wow. Because he was wearing his glasses. He's like, yeah,
I'd never seen that. He kind of knew they were
there, but had never been able to see it before.
I mean, that's one of those little things that just
means, means so much. Yeah. I generally always recommend to
my parents, if they can, if they have a good
developmental optometrist, that's really great to bring in as part
of the
assessment to help them.
Yeah. And so
with pointing, I mean, of course you need shoulder stability
and you need You need the right level of muscle
tone and you need, and you need to be able
to gauge
the force of, of,
um,
and the depth perception because the, the movement goes like
there's an acceleration and there's a deceleration and then you
have to do the same thing in reverse. By the
way, reversal of direction is like universally hard for this
population, whether it's pointing or— Oh, interesting. Moving their body,
like without practice, it's, it's quite hard. And then you
have to do that process,
um, like letter by letter. So it's,
it's an extraordinarily complex and difficult motor task. It's not,
um, like some calling it just pointing is really an
injustice to how hard they have to work to,
to gain access to communication that way.
Which underscores again, um, kind of the whole test Testing
aside, when you hear skeptics talk about just, oh, well,
just put the letterboard on a stand and they have
a point to it that way, and they'll determine, they'll
show if they can actually do it.
I know that's bogus, right? I mean, because it's just,
it's not that simple.
No, it's not. It's not. That's why it's so crucial
to understand the level of challenge and the pathophysiology.
As a practitioner, if you don't have that knowledge, you're
really flying blind working with this population. It's pretty dangerous.
And then with the pointing,
we have these quote unquote tests of not, um, nonverbal
tests of IQ.
Of course, we hate saying that nonverbal because that translates
directly from Latin to without words, and our kids are
not without words. Right, right, right. But people have designed
these
tests, um, To test cognition and understanding,
but things still rely on pointing and eye gaze. So
if you're— so if you're using— if there's no reliable
means of communication and you're using this test on someone,
you're asking them to point to,
uh, a picture or a word or something. And like,
what are you— are you measuring language and understanding, or
are you measuring someone's
motor— Good point.
their motor skill in a very challenging situation in, in
that moment. If they're not valid, so if there is
no reliable means of communication,
it's untestable. You should not be, you should not be
using that test. And we know this from the CP
popu— from the cerebral palsy population,
that these tests are invalid in populations with known motor
impairment.
You shouldn't be using them. Interesting. Talk, talk about that
a little bit more, cuz again, I don't, I don't
know how many people
Realize that. Right. So, so tests of
cognition and intellectual
ability, they're used for educational placements. Yeah. And they're used
for funding decisions.
And this is, this is really serious because you're the—
many educational psychologists are still using these to determine, like,
major life things that really set a person's trajectory on,
on life and, and their family.
And they shouldn't be unless there is a reliable means
of communication.
Cognition and intelligence, they're untestable. You shouldn't be testing.
You're, you're, you're, it's a garbage result that you're, you're
using.
Mm-hmm. And so if, if you,
if you can't test, then the, the safest assumption, the
most logical assumption based on the,
the knowledge that we have in the research and understand
the physiology is that there's no reason to believe
That, um,
the lack of speech
has anything to do with the lack of intelligence. So
you should keep
progressing, keep going on that track until you are proven
otherwise. That's of course the least dangerous assumption. And the
least dangerous assumption, exactly, which is, um,
I mean, it makes all the sense in the world
when you really understand it, but it's, it's
Not practiced very often at all, unfortunately. I mean, maybe
we're seeing it
gaining a little bit more traction, but it feels like
it's just such a fight to, to get there, to
get that. It is. It's only the not— like, only
the nonspeaking population, of course, not just autism, but with
Rett syndrome and Down syndrome, they're expected to prove their,
their intelligence, prove their capacity Their capacity. They're learning before
they are given the right to learn. And whether that's
learning physically,
learning intellectually,
it's, uh, it's really,
it's really tragic.
It is. And dehumanizing.
Yeah.
And, and you think about the damage that's done, not
only obviously the lost opportunity, which is
So obvious. I mean, that's horrible in and of itself,
but the trauma that goes along with it,
you know, the trauma that goes along with knowing that
you're being seen this way as maybe not worth.
And I find when I work with parents,
uh, because of course I never have just one client,
I have the parent and I have the child, and
both need, um, both need support and empowering. And I
know this because I've, I've had experience of being disempowered
by my own fellow rehab med practitioners. So I take
that role very seriously of supporting and encouraging the, the
parents because they don't, um,
they don't need my degrees to be able to be
a great support person and, and therapist their, their child.
It's— no, it's not easy, but like
Like,
you can do this, right? That's, that's the message I
want to send. I never want to make someone dependent
on my service to help them. It's almost— it's also,
I would say, even unethical,
just given that they will need support for— Right.
Uh, yeah, for, you know, long term.
Um,
I was gonna say, the longer,
the longer a parent
goes with that mindset of
My child can't do this. They can't do that. This
is— they're not going to be able to do this.
They don't understand.
It's so
difficult to then— I— for me to come in and
say,
no, what you were told was wrong. And
this is like, this is their potential.
And to, to change that mindset,
it can be very difficult. You have to come at
it very sensitively and,
and patiently.
But it's— Yeah.
But there's a lot of other practitioners out there making
my job much harder because they've set the family on
this trajectory,
and they— which sets the bar very low, and they
lose—
the child loses
much opportunity to fulfill their potential
and quality of life. Right. But the upside is we've
seen example after example of
children or young adults or even adults, once given this
opportunity,
you know, take it and really start to flourish in
ways they're so capable. Yeah. When you give— when you
have high expectations and high effective support, my own son
has like blown my own expectations of what he can
learn physically. out of the water and continues to do
so.
And I
saw what the— I loved your video of Stone jumping
off the diving board. His explanation, it was so great.
I shared that with someone because it was so educational.
So
yeah, it was a good learning moment. It was for
me. I mean, this is what's funny is like I
said, you know, we talked about how we're still learning.
I mean,
This was a couple years ago, as he referenced, you
know, that he was able to do it once or
twice a couple years. And I remember at the time,
again, my mindset was he's afraid to do it because
this is just how we're programmed, right? Like, he got
to the end edge of the— you know, and that's
normal. Like, again, lots of kids are scared to jump
off the diving board, so there's nothing wrong with that.
So I just always thought it was just kind of
a fear factor sort of a thing, that he was
afraid to just take that jump.
Not understanding previously
the impact of apraxia, right? And it was literally like
about a year ago. It's funny because we, for whatever
reason, we didn't happen to go to the pool a
lot last year, so we didn't get a chance to
test the diving board. But I was like, you know
what, because I was seeing so much improvement with him
with his apraxia and his, his motor control and all
that, I'm like, I bet he'll, I bet he'll do
it. Like, you know, this is going to be a
lot easier for him to do it.
So I wasn't surprised. I was thrilled, of course, that
he was able to, you know, they, like he said,
he did it just again and again and again.
That was the cool part.
I should too just mention then, 'cause you used the
word apraxia and that's,
that's considered like we're talking about the same thing, the
DCD apraxia, dyspraxia. That's like a dyspraxia comes from UK
term. And so there's,
um,
Yeah, that's actually part of the problem is that they're
like, people are using the, the terms interchangeably
and that causes confusion, I think, to, to get the
motor impairment,
um,
acknowledged and documented. Not that there's anything, I'm not saying
there's anything wrong with using the word, um, apraxia, but—
Correct. But I, yeah, but I, it, it is the
fact that we have these different terminologies being used. Mm-hmm.
Is definitely contributing to
like a lack of awareness of the, the motor impairment.
So I hope,
like I said, I would like to see just, um,
it not be a dual diagnosis, just the motor impairment.
Motor impairment. Yeah. Yeah. Apraxia specifically refers to mostly the
motor planning part, which is like a very significant part
of the motor dysfunction.
Um, which, yeah, which people should, should be aware of
when they're working with these guys.
Well, yeah, and that makes sense. Maybe there is kind
of a part A, part B sort of a thing.
Like you said, there's just kind of the motor impairment
and then there's the motor planning.
And all this is just, um, you know, it's just
a different language if you're a parent. Yeah, right, right.
I mean, like, you have to learn it. It took
me a long time to really understand it and understand
the concept.
Motor planning. What does that mean? Like, what, you know,
like,
until you see it in practice and understand it, oh,
it really means like planning and being able to, to
do things. You know, the example I always use, you
ask them to go find something and they're able to
do it. Right.
Do things in sequence and,
um, with the right steps. And
yeah,
all those things that seem simple. All right. Well, I
want to talk about, um, Getting back into kind of
the physiotherapy, you, you have a couple of unique areas
of specialty, don't you?
Oh yeah, from— so I, I used to compete for
Alberta in trampoline, and so I have my NCCP Level
1 for just for coaching gymnastics and, and Level 1
and 2 for trampoline. And,
um, and I,
I used to be a Lifeguard 2 instructor back in
the day when I was a teenager.
So of course I, I put my children into swimming
when they were young. I think that's,
um, my son loves water and also just in support
of water safety. But I found that nobody
knew what to do with him in the water. And
in fact, they tried, they wanted to sort of keep
him back with the little kids.
Uh, and when the, and then the age gap was
getting more and more and I, and I didn't like
that. So
I started to figure out how.
Well, I just, I used my,
from my, my own training from my, my mentors with
motor coaching and helping body awareness. And I applied that
with swimming. And then I,
at 40 years old, I, or I mean more than
40, I recertified my swim instructor.
I was like the oldest one in the class. And
so now I— That was, that was— I just love
teaching other swim instructors to, to how to help.
But, um, but I love it. The swimming and gymnastics
are really,
They're, they're great
sports and activities to help gain motor control skills and,
and body awareness. And I really enjoy teaching them, especially
the sport of trampoline. It is a real sport. A
lot of people think it's not just like the jumping
on the trampoline, but the Olympic sport of trampoline where
there's 10 skills in a routine.
And
yeah, I really enjoy coaching my son and, and my
clients in that.
And CrossFit too. Sorry. Sorry. Oh, CrossFit. Oh yeah. I
was gonna say. Yeah, I do. I, I used to
do some CrossFit and then
one thing that it kind of occurred to me that
we can work on motor skills and that's great, but
like part of
fitness is getting your heart rate up. And that's, that
is definitely challenging with this population, but not impossible. So
I started to do,
just take these sort of
beginner CrossFit workouts or ones that I found online or
ones that were designed for kids. And I, I still
had to modify them
and kind of break them down and we do a
little circuit. And so at least with,
with my son, I could get him moving quicker and
getting his heart rate up. And, and
so that's been fun too, to sort of mix in
those workouts.
Do you, do you have those on video? Are you
gonna I should. I'll just put them on video. Yeah.
Because seriously, I mean, you know, those are popular. There's
so many parents that just don't know what to do.
I know. And they know they need to do something.
They know, right? But you need ideas. And I don't—
I needed them too. Like, you, yeah, you really do
need ideas because, and once you, once, once sort of
like you, you get examples of like, oh, you can,
you can do this with them and you can do
this and it really opens up your world and, and
then you that confidence in problem solving. Because I still
have to problem solve through when I'm coaching something.
There's, there's still lots of times where I have to
think, okay, how can I digress this? And, or how,
how can I, um,
what's the component that he's working on? And, and, but
being comfortable with that trial and error and that problem
solving, like, that's okay. Because I, I still do a
lot of sort of
thinking and problem solving, especially with the, the sport skills.
But because that's because you're like smart and qualified and
you think, and you think that way. Most of us
parents were just like, what the heck do we do?
No, I can, I still, I'd reach out to lots
of people to, uh, to, um,
to get their, get their opinion, their eyes when I'm
stuck on problems long, or I'll reach out to a
self-advocate.
That's, I, I think one of,
if for
I have this vision of how people will be educated
and well-trained to work with nonspeaking autism is that there'll
be a, like a, there would be a network of
mentors, mentors for— Yeah. Like parent-to-parent, practitioner-to-practitioner,
but practitioner-to-self-advocate and self-advocate-to-self-advocate.
My best learning comes from kind of discussing challenging cases
and,
and
And
learning from self-advocates
that I continually learn from that. And, and
really, I, I,
there, I, I get frustrated with the clinicians that,
that they feel that they're well-educated and well-trained based on
what they learned in school. Mm-hmm. When they don't have
experience learning from either people Uh,
teachers and, and mentors who have years-long experience working with
communicative nonspeakers or working with communicative nonspeakers yourself.
Because I can't tell you how many times I've been
corrected or I've been, I've given feedback on what I'm
doing and, and, and learned that
something could be better or something was not helpful.
You can't replace that hands-on learning with a book. Oh,
no. And
In a classroom.
So, and I can't even imagine, again, given what's been
learned
just through experience and everything else, just the body of
work over the last
5 to 10 years,
I can't imagine that academics has kept up with that
very well, you know, when you're talking about, right? I
mean, how, how could it even, even in, in that
case?
So they're already kind of coming at it kind of
behind the science, I think, in a lot of the
ways, even though that's true, they think differently.
There in Canada, we have the National Autism Network, and
that's our—
that's the attempt right now to help correct that
knowledge gap. That's what that was kind of outlined as
one of the highest priorities. So
at least here, we're We're— we formed this
organization that hopefully will
make recommendations for Canada's autism strategy and start to
fix— That's good. Fix things so that we see change.
Yeah.
I could only wish that we had that here. Unfortunately,
not, um, not a great place for that right now,
um, when it comes to kind of some of that,
that high-level, um, champion and, and vision For, for our
community. That's one of my,
one of my big complaints. Um,
but let's move on to a couple segments. Let's, let's
lighten it up a little bit. And we'll start with,
um, we'll start with our tip of the week, our
autism tip of the week. And we'll—
Hey parents, gather around, it's time to speak.
We're here with your tip of the week, strategies and
wisdom just for you.
Autism parents, we know what you go through.
All right, it's time for our tip of the week.
And, um, Antigone, what do you have for us?
Tip of the week. Okay,
I thought of 2, and I would say my tip
of the week, especially when you're working with someone to
teach them a new motor skill, or even if it's
an activity of daily living,
My tip would be to give more breaks than you
think they need. Sometimes it's not always obvious how hard
they're working,
but I've learned through mistake and through feedback from
spellers that,
um,
that often, yeah, they need, they need more breaks, especially
to maintain their regulation. Because I have accidentally
pushed someone into dysregulation because I didn't give them enough
break. And I know as a practitioner, if I'm working
with someone who can't tell me when they need a
break, or, um, or a beginner, I'll set a timer
even for if it's 5 minutes or 10 minutes before
I give them a minute or 2 break, uh, because
it's just so easy to forget
sometimes. And then the other tip was,
again, if you're teaching a new motor skill,
always do the skill yourself, even if you think you—
if it's really simple. Like, um,
that's good. Like the other, the other day I was,
uh, one of my clients wanted to learn how to
swing, um, on a swing, like pump his legs by
himself.
And I was teaching it, but then,
um,
I just,
I didn't do it. I, I didn't do it at
first, but then I just thought to check and I
went to do it myself and really think about like,
what is my body doing? What are my muscles doing?
And I realized I sort of missed a component, um,
in that task breakdown. So that would be other tip
is like just Do yourself, even if it's something really
simple and you think you know what steps are involved,
just bring awareness. So you, so you then you, you
put yourself in the other person's shoes of like what
they have to do.
Um, yeah, yeah. Again, it's not natural. I mean, like,
you don't just do it naturally. You actually have to
think about the steps involved. Yeah, they have to think
about it. Yeah.
That's great. Those are both great tips. And especially I
like the breaks because I think that's easy to forget.
I think, um, Again, depending on your personality or mindset,
or yeah, if you come from a
maybe athletic background, you gotta get used to pushing through,
right? Like, we kind of have that pushing through mentality.
Let's just get through it.
And that doesn't always work very well. I mean, that's
not always the best approach. So that was a really
good,
really good tip. All right, we're gonna move forward with
Autism Fact or Fiction. Get QuickTime ready, and here we
go. This is Autism Fact or Fiction. We're breaking down
what's real, what's rumor, and what might surprise you. Let's
go.
Fact or fiction? Motor challenges are usually obvious to trained
professionals.
They are often just so not obvious. Right. We just—
yeah, the norm is that they're, they're not obvious. We're,
we're, we are trained to believe what we see. Mm-hmm.
So that That separation. Because when I, when I
just in my day-to-day life, I see my own son,
I see there's Stellan the person, and then there's Stellan
the body.
And I separate those 2 because, like, for him, they're
separate. And so— Do you ever talk to the body
separately to the— Always. Always. So what— so because once,
once I give the instruction or a statement or a
task or, or something, I'll say, Stellan, uh, let's do
this, or can you do this? Once I see him
unable to do it, then I intervene with support, and
now I'm talking to his body.
And even, um, the, like, Peyton in that interview that
I gave him, he says that really it helps him
because we're trying to,
we're trying to create a shortcut from their mental intent
to their body. So they're, they're working in that moment.
They're working of like, okay, there's the signal. I know
what I want. I need, I'm trying to get the
signal to my body. Mm-hmm.
And so,
so then giving,
um, kind of coaching the body in various ways. Sometimes
you can like do it directional, you can give an
oral prompt. Visual prompts are really great because they're static,
whereas like you say something and then it's, and you
hear it, it's gone. Um, or a tactile, like touching
them. But yeah, I'll even, even,
um, you know, like if, if I'm trying to get
'em, come here, bring your body over here, like. telling
him to,
to, um, getting,
yeah, getting him to sort of, um,
coach his own, coach his own body.
And
yeah, I just, um,
yeah. So that's, that's something that people can, you know,
take away as well. I mean, again, it's something I
hadn't thought about until, until I understood that you could,
that you could actually coach both. Um, and again, in
my example,
There are times, um, Stone, to his credit, said, you
know, a lot of our, our kids, you know, even
older kids, young adults, still, they, they get into those
loops where they crave, you know, the
watching the same video over and over, right? Those YouTube
loops or whatever. And he said, like, look, I don't,
I don't want that anymore. Yeah. I want to move
away. I want to grab, you know, like, I want—
I know I, I want to put that behind me.
And like, he had a very eloquent, um,
way of talking about it when, when he and I
had a conversation a few months ago. And so we,
you know, basically kind of went cold turkey, but the,
the body still wants it, right? I was just gonna
say, what? Exactly. And so I literally said, I'm like,
Stone, I understand, you know, I know your brain doesn't
want it. Your body does. I get that. I hear
you, but your brain, remember your brain, your brain would
be so mad if you listen to your body right
now. He's like, okay, you know, he gets it. And
then, you know, there's, it's It's amazing. It's really— It's
crazy, right? Just when you see, like, you hear what
you— like, you will read what they would want to
be doing, and their body is doing literally the opposite.
Not even like what something else, but the opposite. And
one of my other parent colleagues, I liked her. She
coined the term, um, opposite land. It's like, welcome to
opposite land. Like, it's such a good— I love that.
Right? I love that too. Yeah. Because this is a
bizarre condition when you, when you see, when they say
one thing
Uh, and like, we, you know, you can confirm it
with their words because their words are like, are what
you can trust. Yeah. And their bodies are so unreliable
that, uh, it, it can be, it really, it can
be impossible to differentiate. Sometimes with enough observation, you know
their body, you can, you can
get to spot intentional versus unintentional movement.
Sometimes you can't tell the difference. And I even, even
now I can't, like, until I I get it right
from my son's hand and letterboard. Right. Yeah, same. And
as, as,
as much progress as Stone has made with his— actually,
his intentional speech has improved greatly. And again, it's much
more consistent in terms of matching up his, his actual
intent. It's still not 100%, like, and so there'll be
times that his speech will sound convincing, but, you know,
to your point, You sit down like, okay, I'm gonna
verify.
Tell me what you want. And he's like, no, don't
do what— you know, like, don't do what I'm telling
you to do. Like, it's just like, well, he's still
saying that. Like, it's, it's wild. It's really wild. That's,
that's the— That's, that's the world we live. That's the
world they live in too. Yeah, that's the chaos. All
right, this is, uh, this one I'm kind of looking
forward to because I, because I have a feeling you'll
have, have something good to share here. Well, I want
to do the Our parent confession. Routines can go astray.
Found socks in the fridge one day.
Laughter's the best remedy. Hey, we're just finding our own
way. Mom-Dad Confessions every week. Sharing joys and moments we
seek. Honest tales that make us unique. Join the club,
we're never meek.
All right. So again, this is our time that we,
we show our humility and our humanity, that we're, we're
just people too, right? That we have exactly moments that
we look back at and just say, oh
man, I can't believe I did that.
I have a lot actually to accumulate the, uh,
my mistakes, but when
So in the beginning, so when, yeah, Stella was about
4 and 3/4 and I,
I stumbled upon the letterboard and, and I was taught
that, uh, that I,
I, I, I kind of, I grew to understand that
what I was seeing was not,
not the reality.
And, and this was, yes, we'd started using the letterboard
and, and I, I saw, like, I saw early on
I could, what they were teaching me, I, I could
see it. He wasn't communicating open-ended yet, but Mm-hmm. I
saw his potential. And then
that
grief of, like, it was probably about a month of,
like, crying because I had these flashbacks of things
that I did
where I confused
won't versus can't. Mm-hmm. Where I would, like, discipline him.
something that I thought he was refusing to do when
it was he can't, when he can't. Oh yeah. And
so I remember when he was,
he was, um,
young and he had, he, I'd like finished cleaning and
he, we had this bin of Lego and he,
and he dumped it out
and, uh,
and I got mad at him for that and I
asked him to like, okay, put the, put the Lego
back in, in the bin.
And he didn't. And I asked him again and he,
and he didn't. And I,
Sorry to— So yeah, I sent him to his room.
He started to cry.
And,
but I kind of like, I was
standing my ground stupidly. And I, but I, I looked
at him and there was this moment and like he
looked up at the ceiling and he had this look
on his face. Usually, often his, not always, often his,
his facial expressions are not the most reliable, but this
look gave me pause because it, it looked like he
was so desperate. It looked like he was saying something
like, like, God, please help me
get better and, and, and like, help me. I can't,
I can't do this like that. I just, my brain
went like,
it gave me pause. And then, but then I let
it go.
And so that flash, I, I,
when I learned that
he understood everything,
and then I, I would get that flashback of,
of disciplining him for the Lego. And, and there's a
lot of times that I just assumed he couldn't Like
experiences, uh, you know, I don't know, going out to
watch his sister's
dance recital and just things I
decided that they were too hard for him, so I
didn't give him the opportunity to try.
Mm-hmm. Even recently with art, even I'm still correcting myself
because I kind of for a while had this idea
that like fine motor art, drawing and, and piano was
like,
that's gonna be too hard.
No, he's in piano lessons. And— Oh, great. I took
a course, some RPM provider,
on how to support and adapt art. And then it
opened up my thinking, my in-the-box thinking of how you
can properly support and how you can start to,
again, like high expectations and high support. Well,
like there's no limits.
Yeah.
It's hard, you know, it's hard, like we've talked about
earlier, to kind of deprogram ourselves. There's a lot,
there's, you know, there's just a lot there. And, um,
man, you brought back, you know, a memory
for me as well. It's kind of similar when Stone's
really— I won't go through the whole thing, but, but
that look, I,
I got that look.
And, you know, at that moment, that was just kind
of like, uh,
It was bittersweet because
it confirmed to me that there was more inside
than he was able to share, which I'd always
wanted to believe and kind of believe, but it confirmed,
right? And, but then also showed me, you know, felt,
I just felt like just such a tool, you know,
just like, just like, oh man, I can't believe. Yeah.
I beat myself up for a while for that. I
don't anymore. I don't anymore because again, I just know
better, do better. No, better do better. You know what?
They get it too, right? Think, I mean, they're amazing.
Yeah. They're so forgiving and so understanding and, you know,
they know we're doing our best. I think that's, you
know, it's all we can do. And again, for all
the, all you parents out there, just give yourself. And
that's one of the reasons I have this segment is
to show that, you know,
I mean, we all make mistakes. I mean, this, there's,
there's no, uh,
There's no guidebook for any of us, right? Like, we're
all just trying to figure it out. And it, it
is lit— and it not, not only does it help
to kind of hang on to that, if that's— there's
anxiety or, or guilt there, um, it, it can be
a hindrance because our, our children are so sensitive to
the, the states of the people around them, including especially
the people who are supporting them, the rate our own
regulation states. And yeah, he's been— I've been told like
that's It—
my own
mental state, it really can have an impact on his.
Yes, on his. And then subsequently, of course, that affects
his motor control and his,
um, triple effect. Yeah, absolutely. No, that's, that's another great
point.
Well, Antigone, we ran up against our time. I knew
we would. I knew we'd have so much to talk
about. I just want to thank you so much for
helping us understand that communication is not only about speech
language or intelligence. It's also about whether a person can
organize their body
well enough to express what they know.
If there's someone wants to get in touch with you,
do you have a website? Do you have an email?
Anything you want to share for people? Yeah,
I can give you my email. I'm happy to answer
questions and consult. I don't have— my website is not
ready at the moment, but I'm— Okay, that's fine. Yeah.
We'll, uh, we'll include that. We'll put that in the
show notes. Um, sounds good. So people who have questions,
but, uh, again, thank you. It's, it's been a delight
having you here, as I knew it would. And for
everyone out there listening, thank you for listening to The
Lighter Side of the Spectrum.
Please subscribe, share this episode, and help us continue expanding
the conversation around communication rights and presumed competence.